A Guide to the Papers of the Charlottesville Department of Parks and Recreation 1938-1973
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Charlottesville Department of Parks and Recreation 1938-1973
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11347
There are ca. 1220 items.
This collection of papers pertaining to the Charlottesville Department of Parks and Recreation consists of ca. 1220 items, covering 1938-1973. Included are correspondence, records and other papers, photographs, and newspaper clippings. The majority of these records were kept by Nannie Burwell Crow, director of the Charlottesville Department of Recreation for twenty-nine years until her retirement in August 1966.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This material was given to the Library by Mrs. Viola Pugh of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December 11, 1997.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, 1945-1959, of Nannie Burwell Crow and Frank M. Smith is concerned with daily business of the Department of Recreation, budget concerns, and special recommendations. An August 31, 1955 letter from E[dward] R. Slaughter discusses the possibility of Albemarle Lake being incorporated into the recreation program. Items of interest include: Press Release, "National Recreation Citations Awarded in Charlottesville"(June 15, 1956); Constitution of the Recreation Advisory Board (November 21, 1956); and, Petition to have a supervised playground area on the McIntire Park property(fall 1957). There are three letters, October 30 and November 11, 1957 and March 22, 1958 concerning the Citizens Recreation Committee. There is a letter, May 19, 1958, from James E. Bowen, Jr., City Manager, commending the Recreation Board and Parks Department. There are several letters between May 1958 and October 1959 pertaining to the purchase of surplus aircraft by municipal recreation departments. A February 26, 1959 letter from Frank M. Smith to James K. Bowen, Jr. provides recommendations for capital improvements for city playgrounds. During March and April 1959 there are numerous letters of thanks for contributions; and, during May and June, there are letters about the capital improvements. On July 13, 1959, William M. Hay, representative for the National Recreation Association, gives advice on giving civic leadership to the recreation and parks movement. James E. Bowen, Jr., City Manager, provides recommendations and estimates for capital improvements for the city, including recreation.
There are ca. 350 photograghs, 1938-1966, of people and scenes and events pertaining to the Department of Parks and Recreation. Several Charlottesville parks and events are represented: "Magic Show," Meade park (1938-1939); spray pool, Belmont Park (1950s); wading pool, Forest [Hill] Park (1954); "Doll Show," Belmont Park (1955); "Show Wagon," Meade Park (1955); picnic, McIntire Park (1956); Forest Hill Park (1959); various events, Belmont Park (1960); various events, Rives Park (1962); pool, McIntire Park (1963); Rives Park (1966); Bibb Park (1966); and, Meade Park (1966). There are several photograghs of African-Americans: male youths playing pool at Carver Recreation Center (1961); Children involved in various activities (1963); and, the Arts and Crafts Exhibit at Westhaven (1965). A Variety of events are depicted: annual baby show, 1938-1959; dances, 1948-1958; Halloween and costume parties, 1948-1961; parades, 1938 and 1964; plays, 1955-1957; skating, 1957-1964; sports, including basketball, boxing, football, pool, softball, tennis, and zelball, 1938-1961; and, the "Show Wagon," 1953-1955.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by item.
Contents List
- Cash Book of the Department of Recreation 1938-1939 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Nannie Burwell Crow, director, and Frank M. Smith, secretary 1945-1959 (Box 1)
- Memoranda and Receipts belonging to Nannie Burwell Crow 1939-1940 (Box 1)
- Minutes of the Recreation Advisory Board 1945-1970, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Monthly Reports of the Department of Recreation 1934-1953, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs 1938-1966, 8 folders (Box 2)
- Record Book of the Department of Recreation kept by Nannie Burwell Crow 1956-1967 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1959-1964, electrostatic copies (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1964-1966, electrostatic copies (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1971-1973, electrostatic copies (Box 2)
- Thesis: "An Investigation for the Design of a Community Recreation Building for Charlottesville, Virginia" by Samuel Edward Darnell, University of Virginia School of Architecture 1955 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1955-1959, loose bound volume (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings 1943-1946, paper fragile (Box P-21)
- Plans for playground shelter n.d. (Box M-20)
- Plans for "Show Wagon" n.d. (Box M-20)